Support Admin Watch on kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
دعم الإدارة، شاهد على kissasia.cam أو kisskh.org
Get out.
اخرج.
Get out!
اخرج!
Deji.
اهدأ.
What do you want now?
ماذا تريد الآن؟
I worked all day today.
لقد عملت طوال اليوم.
My hands are raw and bleeding.
يداي متقرحتان وتنزفان.
And I reek of manure.
ورائحة السماد تفوح مني.
Just now, I fought fiercely
قبل قليل، قاتلت بشراسة
with my lifelong friend over prejudice.
مع صديقي الذي رافقني طوال حياتي، وتغلبنا على التحيز.
Only now do I realize
الآن فقط أدركت ذلك
what kind of life you lived
أي نوع من الحياة عشت
back at the Balu estate.
العودة إلى عزبة بالو.
What kind of suffering you endured.
أي نوع من المعاناة تحملتها؟
Deji.
اهدأ.
I used to think
كنت أعتقد
that I liked you.
أنني كنت معجباً بك.
Now I see how much of a jerk I was.
الآن أدرك كم كنتُ أحمق.
I liked you as if you were a thing.
كنت معجباً بك كما لو كنت شيئاً ما.
Like how one admires
مثل الإعجاب
a beautiful antelope.
ظبي جميل.
I never saw you as an equal person.
لم أرك يوماً كشخص مساوٍ لي.
After going through all this,
بعد المرور بكل هذا،
I now understand
لقد فهمت الآن
what equality is.
ما هي المساواة.
And what true affection really is.
وما هي المودة الحقيقية حقاً.
Deji.
اهدأ.
Gongba Mocuo (I'm sorry).
غونغبا موكو (أنا آسف).
Brother Gao Yuan.
الأخ غاو يوان.
Even though my hatred for Balu Yundan
على الرغم من كراهيتي لبالو يوندان
was once heavier than the snow mountains,
كانت في يوم من الأيام أثقل من الجبال الثلجية،
I still forgave him.
ما زلتُ قد سامحته.
After all, successfully reforming him
في النهاية، إصلاحه بنجاح
will be a huge shock to other noble youths.
سيكون ذلك بمثابة صدمة كبيرة للشباب النبلاء الآخرين.
The significance is profound.
الأهمية بالغة.
But as Balu Yundan and Deji grow closer,
لكن مع ازدياد تقارب بالو يوندان وديجي،
asking me to agree to them being together...
يطلبون مني الموافقة على أن يكونوا معًا...
I can't do it.
لا أستطيع فعل ذلك.
I don't believe
أنا لا أعتقد
that a former young master,
ذلك السيد الشاب السابق،
who had everything served to him,
الذي كان كل شيء يُقدّم له،
can truly bend his back to do hard labor.
يستطيع حقاً أن يثني ظهره للقيام بأعمال شاقة.
What if
ماذا إذا
this is just an act to deceive Deji?
هل هذا مجرد تمثيل لخداع ديجي؟
Deji.
اهدأ.
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
What's wrong?
ما هو الخطأ؟
Sister.
أخت.
I saw the letter you wrote to Battalion Commander Yi.
لقد اطلعت على الرسالة التي كتبتها إلى قائد الكتيبة يي.
I'm sorry.
أنا آسف.
Are you angry, Sister?
هل أنتِ غاضبة يا أختي؟
Sister isn't angry.
الأخت ليست غاضبة.
I've been doubting
كنت أشك في ذلك.
Balu Yundan's sincerity towards you.
إخلاص بالو يوندان تجاهك.
But today, seeing him work hard
لكن اليوم، رؤيته وهو يعمل بجد
and protect you so fiercely
وأحميك بشدة
when you were bullied...
عندما تعرضت للتنمر...
I think
أظن
he must genuinely like you.
لا بد أنه معجب بك حقاً.
Well, I don't necessarily like him either.
حسنًا، أنا أيضًا لا أحبه بالضرورة.
Our little Deji has really grown up.
لقد كبر ديجي الصغير حقاً.
Whether you like him or not,
سواء أعجبك أم لا،
Sister won't stand in your way.
لن تقف أختك في طريقك.
If he can truly reform himself,
إذا استطاع حقاً أن يُصلح نفسه،
Sister respects your choice.
أختي تحترم اختيارك.
Sister.
أخت.
You're so good to me.
أنت لطيف جداً معي.
Hmm?
همم؟
You've worked hard.
لقد بذلت جهداً كبيراً.
Put me down!
أنزلني!
Sister, have mercy!
يا أختي، ارحميني!
March, 1959.
مارس 1959.
The reactionary upper-class clique in Xizang
الزمرة الرجعية من الطبقة العليا في شيزانغ
openly violated the Seventeen-Point Agreement,
انتهك علناً اتفاقية النقاط السبعة عشر،
launching a full-scale armed rebellion
إطلاق تمرد مسلح واسع النطاق
in an attempt to split the motherland.
في محاولة لتقسيم الوطن الأم.
The Chinese People's Liberation Army was ordered to suppress the rebellion,
تلقى جيش التحرير الشعبي الصيني أوامر بقمع التمرد.
safeguarding national unity and the fundamental interests
حماية الوحدة الوطنية والمصالح الأساسية
of all ethnic groups in Xizang.
من بين جميع المجموعات العرقية في شيزانغ.
Balu Yundan.
بالو يوندان.
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
I'm not staying at the Tibetan Public School.
لن أقيم في المدرسة العامة التبتية.
Why won't they let former noble youths go to Xizang to help suppress the rebellion?
لماذا لا يسمحون لشباب النبلاء السابقين بالذهاب إلى شيزانغ للمساعدة في قمع التمرد؟
I want to go back and persuade my father.
أريد العودة وإقناع والدي.
Is there a problem?
هل هناك مشكلة؟
Then where will you go?
ثم إلى أين ستذهب؟
An eagle will not build its nest
النسر لا يبني عشه
on a cliff that despises it.
على جرف يحتقره.
My path
مساري
lies where the clouds drift.
يقع حيث تنجرف الغيوم.
It's none of your concern.
هذا ليس من شأنك.
Hear me out first.
استمع إلي أولاً.
Then you can leave.
ثم يمكنك المغادرة.
I know your heart is with your homeland
أعلم أن قلبك مع وطنك
and with your father.
ومع والدك.
You want to go back to join the suppression
تريد العودة للانضمام إلى القمع
and the Democratic Reform.
والإصلاح الديمقراطي.
We understand this sentiment.
نتفهم هذا الشعور.
Then why won't you let me go back?
فلماذا لا تسمح لي بالعودة؟
Precisely because you are a highland eagle,
لأنك نسر مرتفعات،
we must protect your wings.
يجب علينا حماية جناحيك.
The organization isn't sending students of noble birth
لا ترسل المنظمة طلاباً من أصول نبيلة
or those under eighteen
أو أولئك الذين تقل أعمارهم عن ثمانية عشر عامًا
back at this time.
بالعودة إلى هذا الوقت.
It's not that we don't trust you.
ليس الأمر أننا لا نثق بك.
It's because we fear you might get hurt.
ذلك لأننا نخشى أن تتعرض للأذى.
As long as your hearts are towards the light,
ما دامت قلوبكم متجهة نحو النور،
and you don't participate in the rebellion,
وأنت لا تشارك في التمرد،
you are safe here
أنت بأمان هنا
at the Tibetan Public School.
في المدرسة العامة التبتية.
You are protected.
أنت محمي.
Furthermore,
بالإضافة إلى،
staying at school
ابقَ في المدرسة
also allows you to contribute to the suppression and reform.
كما يتيح لك المساهمة في القمع والإصلاح.
Your wings are your own.
جناحيك ملكك أنت.
If you insist on leaving,
إذا أصررت على المغادرة،
I can't stop you.
لا أستطيع منعك.
But before you go,
لكن قبل أن تذهب،
you should think about
يجب أن تفكر في
why you crossed mountains to come here in the first place.
لماذا عبرت الجبال لتصل إلى هنا في المقام الأول؟
Think about who you truly want to protect.
فكّر في من تريد حمايته حقاً.
It is precisely for Deji's sake
هذا من أجل ديجي تحديداً
that I must go back.
يجب عليّ العودة.
In Xizang,
في شيزانغ
serf owners and serfs
ملاك الأقنان والأقنان
are like heaven
إنها مثل الجنة
and earth.
والأرض.
Only by spreading the idea of equality for all
فقط من خلال نشر فكرة المساواة للجميع
to every Tibetan person
إلى كل شخص تبتي
will Deji and I
هل سأفعل أنا وديجي ذلك؟
have a chance.
ستتاح لك الفرصة.
Besides, I already wrote to my father,
إضافة إلى ذلك، فقد كتبت بالفعل إلى والدي،
telling him to see the situation clearly
يطلب منه أن يرى الموقف بوضوح
and support the reform.
ودعم الإصلاح.
Good.
جيد.
Then keep writing letters.
ثم استمر في كتابة الرسائل.
Tell your family everything
أخبر عائلتك بكل شيء
you've seen and learned here in the interior.
لقد رأيتم وتعلمتم هنا في الداخل.
Only then
عندها فقط
will the new Xizang we wish to see
هل سيكون شيزانغ الجديد هو ما نرغب برؤيته؟
arrive sooner.
الوصول مبكراً.
Comrade Balu Yundan,
الرفيق بالو يوندان،
I can help deliver your letters.
يمكنني المساعدة في توصيل رسائلك.
In the past
في الماضي
Hatred coiled in my heart like a venomous snake.
الكراهية تلتف في قلبي كأفعى سامة.
But today
لكن اليوم
I saw your desire to return to Xizang to quell the rebellion
لقد رأيت رغبتك في العودة إلى شيزانغ لإخماد التمرد
and your heart set on persuading reform.
وقلبك مصمم على إقناع الناس بالإصلاح.
It's as sincere and bright as sunlight on a snowy mountain.
إنها صادقة ومشرقة كضوء الشمس على جبل مغطى بالثلوج.
Only then did I realize
عندها فقط أدركت
that I was blinded by the shadows of the past.
أنني كنت أعمى بسبب ظلال الماضي.
Classmate Balu Yundan,
زميل الدراسة بالو يوندان،
please forgive my narrow-mindedness.
أرجو أن تسامحوني على ضيق أفقه.
In truth, when I fell gravely ill
في الحقيقة، عندما مرضت مرضاً خطيراً
and Deji came to care for me,
ثم جاء ديجي ليعتني بي،
I completely abandoned the idea of being a young master.
لقد تخليت تماماً عن فكرة أن أكون سيداً شاباً.
I want to be a true person,
أريد أن أكون إنساناً حقيقياً،
a person just like all of you.
شخص مثلكم جميعاً.
From today onward,
ابتداءً من اليوم فصاعداً،
we are true classmates
نحن زملاء دراسة حقيقيون
and comrades fighting side by side for Xizang's tomorrow.
والرفاق الذين يقاتلون جنباً إلى جنب من أجل غد شيزانغ.
Deji,
اهدأ،
I'm returning to Xizang soon.
سأعود إلى شيزانغ قريباً.
You must take good care of yourself at school.
يجب عليك أن تعتني بنفسك جيداً في المدرسة.
Don't worry, Sister.
لا تقلقي يا أختي.
My heart holds you, Sister,
قلبي يحتضنكِ يا أختي.
and also holds our Xizang folks.
كما أنها تضم ​​شعبنا من شيزانغ.
That's why I must quickly master medicine,
لذلك يجب عليّ أن أتقن الطب بسرعة.
just like you, Sister,
مثلكِ تماماً يا أختي،
to become someone useful to our homeland.
أن نصبح شخصاً مفيداً لوطننا.
On this return to Xizang,
في هذه العودة إلى شيزانغ،
will you see Brother Gao Yuan?
هل ستلتقي بالأخ غاو يوان؟
Mm-hmm.
ممم.
The snowy mountains
الجبال الثلجية
and the sacred lake
والبحيرة المقدسة
will surely guide us to meet.
سيرشدنا ذلك بالتأكيد إلى اللقاء.
See you in Xizang.
أراك في شيزانغ.
Crossing the final mountain,
عبور الجبل الأخير،
Nedong County is right before our eyes.
تقع مقاطعة نيدونغ أمام أعيننا مباشرة.
Brother Gao Yuan,
الأخ غاو يوان،
Can the wind here hear my heartbeat?
هل تستطيع الرياح هنا سماع دقات قلبي؟
Each beat is calling your name.
كل إيقاع ينادي اسمك.
Mm.
مم.
Meiduo,
ميدو,
Look.
ينظر.
Nedong County is right ahead.
تقع مقاطعة نيدونغ في الأمام مباشرة.
Brother Gao Yuan is right there.
الأخ غاو يوان موجود هناك.
You must be overjoyed, darn it.
لا بد أنك في غاية السعادة، اللعنة.
Let's go.
دعنا نذهب.
Meiduo.
ميدو.